<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe examination; of a certaine pamphlet lately printed in Scotland, and intituled: Ladensium autocatacrisis, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E47_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21801</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871507</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123918</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123918)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E47[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe examination; of a certaine pamphlet lately printed in Scotland, and intituled: Ladensium autocatacrisis, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>"Without titlepage, and ending abruptly with p. 56. No more seems to have been published."  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ladensium autocatacrisis.</term>
               <term>Large supplement of the Canterburian self-conviction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Pamphlets --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:123918:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123918:1"/>
            <head>A Briefe Examination; Of a Certaine Pamphlet lately Printed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Intituled: <hi>Ladenſium Autocatacriſis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was written in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and directed to the high Court of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> at their laſt ſitting, a bitter and malicious Pamphlet, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled: <hi>Ladenſium Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catacriſis: The Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſelfe-conviction: Or, An evident Domonstration of the avowed Arminianiſme, Poperie and Tyrannie of that Faction, by their owne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:123918:2"/> The purpoſe of this Worke ſpeakes it ſelfe in the Title; namely, to brand many particular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in this Church with Heterodoxie of Opinions, and that under the name of a Faction, and a Faction united in my Lo. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as in their Common Head. Which Accuſation of Heterodoxie in Opinions will be here found falſe and frivolous, and never a one of theſe Divines but will ſhake off this Pamphlet, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did the venemous Beaſt, into the fire, and feele himſelfe never the worſe for it: But were it ſo, that ſome men in their opinions, and writings, did depart from the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of this Church; yet to affirme, they combine to doe it as a Faction, and to aſcribe the Conduct of that Faction to my Lo. of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> without manifeſt and convincing Proofe, is a meere Calumny, and indeed but the ſpume of that Malice with which they proſecute him, endeavouring through his ſides to wound the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to draw one Line of Confuſion over all. Yet that the Matter may carry ſome Colour, this Vndertaker, whoever he be, hath eveſdropped all his <hi>Grace's</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, to ſee what he may poſſibly diſtort to any ill meaning; Concerning which, though we might briefly anſwer, what <note n="a" place="margin">Ep. ad Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeſar.</note> S. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaks in like caſe for himſelfe: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that is in effect; <hi>A furious Zelot is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Iudge of the Writings of a well-affected Proteſtant:</hi> Yet I ſhall endeavour to lay the Particulars before you, very briefly and faithfully; that ſo when you ſee the whole reckoning together, you may judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on his <hi>Grace's</hi> part, in any thing he hath written, any juſt cauſe hath beene given, of all this Clamour
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123918:2"/> raiſed againſt him, and all the unreverent Contumelies which are here caſt upon him. Archbiſhops were not wont to be thus handled; but in this Age of the World, it were a ridiculous thing to ſend theſe Men to the Councells of <note n="b" place="margin">Can. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Can. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Carthage,</hi> or <note n="d" place="margin">Can. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> to learne better manners in this behalfe: Now is a time with them to hiſſe at all the Canons and Councels of the Chriſtian World; and inſtead of ſuch ſuperſtitious and out-worne ſtuffe, to idolize their owne new Bookes of Diſcipline, which leave both their tongues and pens free, <note place="margin">Iud. 5.8.</note> to <hi>deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeake evill of dignities.</hi> But whether theſe things proceed from hearts ſeaſoned with the leaſt tincture of Grace, or any ſyncere Affection to Religion and true Piety (a thing ſo much pretended and boaſted now adayes) whether it be Chriſtian-like, ſo barbarouſly and uncivilly to ſlander men of Place and Eminence, in the face of a Kingdome, wherein by Gods Ordinance, and the eſtabliſhed Lawes, they are (under the Kings Majeſty) appointed the chief Guides and Governours of the Church: that any ſort of men, eſpecially the meaneſt, ſhould be permitted ſuch an unbridled licence againſt them; whether, I ſay, it be Chriſtian-like, or befitting the honour of a Reformed Church, though men may have forgotten to judge, God will ſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>2. But before I meddle with matters of <hi>Opinion,</hi> I muſt expoſtulate ſome things with this Authour, which come rather to the nature of <hi>Fact,</hi> and ſerve to make up a great part of the noyſe. Where firſt, Sir, what meane you by this Title, or Frontiſpice, <hi>Laden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium Autocatacriſis, The Canterburians Selfe-conviction?</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:123918:3"/> Expound you <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Selfe-conviction?</hi> Sure the word ſignifies, <hi>Selfe-condemning:</hi> and <hi>Selfe-convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi> is not <hi>Selfe-condemning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But not to detaine you in this ſlip: Why <hi>Selfe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction?</hi> Becauſe they have written ſomething, out of which, you think, you can convict them? But your <hi>Convicting</hi> them, is not <hi>Selfe-convicting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>3. And thirdly; why, a <hi>Demonſtration by their owne Confeſsions?</hi> Doe they <hi>confeſſe</hi> the Fact? Indeed you have raked together many Sayings and Sentences out of their Bookes to prove them <hi>Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Maintainers of Tyranny;</hi> but doe they anſwer guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to all this? Sure your Purpoſe is but to fright the poore Men with this <hi>Mormo</hi> of your Title. Otherwiſe we know, an Accuſation, though taken from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>owne mouth,</hi> does not preſently inferre his owne <hi>Confeſsion;</hi> for words may be miſapplied, or miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: Nor to bee convicted by another man, though out of his owne mouth; is to be <hi>ſelfe-convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted:</hi> nor to be ſo convicted, even <hi>by himſelfe,</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to be <hi>ſelfe-condemned.</hi> This is ſuch ſtuffe, that the Parties concerned, as <note n="e" place="margin">De Pallio.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeleon, Ridebunt illicò audaciam &amp; Graeciam Nominis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <p>4. But in your <note n="*" place="margin">We offer to inſtruct to the full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the whole world of free and inprejudicate mindes, not by fleeing reports, not by probable likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, not by the ſentences of the graveſt and most ſolemne Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this Land, our two laſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblies, and late Parliament. All there meanes of Probation wee ſhall ſet aſide, and take us alone to the Mouth of our very Adverſaries.</note> Preface you tell us, you could have uſed other Proofes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide their owne Bookes: 1 <hi>Flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</hi> 2 <hi>Probable likelihoods.</hi> 3 <hi>The ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the two last generall Aſſemblies and late Parliament in Scotland:</hi> where the <hi>two firſt</hi> are, if you marke it, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, very ſtrong proofs: and though you ſeeme to paſſe them by, yet you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123918:3"/> have truſted them as much as any. But for the <hi>third,</hi> if my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and theſe his <hi>Canterburians,</hi> as you pleaſe to call them, were then and there in your two Aſſemblies and Parliament condemned of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, being, as they ſtand in your <hi>Index,</hi> all <hi>Engliſh-men:</hi> may they not reaſonably plead what he doth in the Tragedie? <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>A ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of one Countrey ought not to be judged in another: Ne, uſurpata altarum partium ſollicitudine, Bellum inter ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citarent,</hi> as S. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Spartam, tibi quae contigit, orna:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nobis fuerint Cura Mycenae.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> But the truth is, it is enough with men of your Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to call your Adverſaries, <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Arminians,</hi> or what you pleaſe, your Adherents will believe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your bare Word. Do but you ſay it, and all the Proteſtations, Oathes, Subſcriptions, all the art and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry they can uſe, ſhall never ſufficiently purge them of it. So that, if now, <hi>ex ſuperabundanti,</hi> you will not <hi>ſay</hi> it onely, but <hi>prove</hi> it too; very good reaſon, you ſhould grace your performance with ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary inſcription. Let it be therefore <hi>Autocatacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> a very <hi>Selfe-conviction,</hi> though it be indeed neither, nor one of theſe, the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>Once more; If you will needs miſtake theſe men to be <hi>Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>upholders of Tyranny;</hi> was it not enough <hi>to call</hi> them <hi>ſuch?</hi> No; they are <hi>Ladenſians, Canterburians:</hi> as if my Lord of <hi>Canterburie</hi> had led them into theſe Opinions; when you cannot be ſo blinde, as not to ſee, who their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and Abettors are, in all this, as you call it, <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Examine but your owne Margin, there you ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123918:4"/> finde <note n="a" place="margin">P. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Ignatius,</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">P. 51</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">P. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>Optatus,</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">P. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">P. 38, 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">P. 82.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> 
                  <note n="i" place="margin">P 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 57, 59, 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> 
                  <note n="k" place="margin">P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> 
                  <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> 
                  <note n="l" place="margin">P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard,</hi> and other like: all vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together by you with theſe moderne men. Are all theſe <hi>Canterburians?</hi> For let the reader turne, I ſay, and ſee, if they ſtand not in your margin under the ſame condemnation, all. You pretend againſt the Pope, but you are his friend many wayes; eſpecially in this, a more profuſe benefactor to him, than <hi>Pipin, Charlemaigne,</hi> or any other. You give him Eaſt and Weſt, the ſuffrage of all Chriſtendome, ſide and wide, the conſent of the beſt Writers in elder and later times; They are all for the Pope, by your Donation, all invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in one common guilt of ſupporting his <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hierarchie.</hi> The voice of the Donatiſts was, <hi>Nos ſoli manſimus,</hi> the whole world is apoſtate; <hi>Our congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> remaines the onely true Church: but yours muſt be, <hi>Nos ſoli fuimus;</hi> we are the firſt, and before us there was never any; never, in all the centuries of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, any ſuch doctrine or diſcipline to be found, as you have deviſed. And your performance here, is not againſt the <hi>Canterburians</hi> onely; but even a generall inditement of all times and ages for ſuperſtition and hereſie. Onely this humour of nick-naming is none of the neweſt, whether we regard either <hi>fact,</hi> or <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Thoſe that ſtuck to <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, an innocent man, and refuſed to communicate with his unworthy ſucceſſour <hi>Arſacius,</hi> were called <note n="m" place="margin">Socrat. l. 6. c. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioannitae, Iohnists,</hi> forſooth. And thoſe, that in the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Councell maintained the Orthodoxe Faith, together with S. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> againſt the fect of <hi>Nestorius,</hi> were by that Sect termed, <note n="n" place="margin">Apud Bin. 10.1. par. 2. p. 287. Colon. 1618.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrilliani, Cyrillians.</hi> Iuſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123918:4"/> thus, the conformable Miniſtery of this Kingdome, that in their books and practice maintaine the doctrine and diſcipline of this Church, which my Lord of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> doth in the prime place, muſt be, <hi>Canterburians:</hi> This is the ingenuity of the title prefixed to your book: <hi>dignum patinâ operculum;</hi> a fit cover for ſuch a diſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>6. Now in your Preface, this <hi>chimaera</hi> of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburian</hi> faction and the Prelates, muſt bee ſtigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for the authours of all the miſchiefes in the world; thereby to induce the high Court of Parliament to expell, <hi>non Tarquinium, ſed Regnum;</hi> not the Biſhops, but even the Biſhopricks. Which yet were not equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to blame the <hi>office,</hi> for the <hi>men.</hi> And whereas it hath been ever your way, in your accuſatory writings, to ſhift from <hi>things,</hi> to <hi>perſons;</hi> let mee tell you, It is the knowne practice of ſchiſmaticks: <hi>Me facit cauſam, cum defeciſſet in causâ,</hi> ſaies St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> of <hi>Petilianus.</hi> When hee failes in his <hi>cauſe,</hi> hee miſtakes <hi>mee</hi> for the <hi>cauſe:</hi> And, in <hi>Lib. cont. Fortunatum, Alia eſt quaeſtio de Fide, alia de moribus.</hi> And, <hi>Iſtae haereticorum machinae ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Hierom cont. Ruff.</hi> Thus the Prelates, they <hi>declare,</hi> they <hi>proclaime</hi> in the Kings name, they <hi>change the face of the Court,</hi> you ſay, into what ſhape they pleaſe: They doubtleſſe have <hi>ſome ſecret deſigne,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Praef. p. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>when both Nations by mutuall wounds, are diſabled for defence againſt the common enemy, to bring in</hi> France, <hi>or</hi> Spaine, <hi>ſpightfull Nations, and the hereditary enemies of our Religion and Iland: and this they doe, when the teares of his Majeſties onely ſiſter, the deſolation of her moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſubjects, the captivity and baniſhment of her hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children ſhould command, as in pity, to put up all our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123918:5"/> homeward quarrels, though they evere both great and many, nor ſhould we be induced by any allurement, by any terrour, to ſubmit our ſelves as vallets and pages to the execution of the luſts, the furies, and outragious counſels of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury <hi>and his dependers; ſince the maine grievances both of Church and State, have no other originall, no other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine on earth, but thoſe men.</hi> All which is a Libell even againſt common ſence, and needes no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
               <p>Beſides, this mans falſhood had bin much more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, if he had kept himſelf within civill language; for poſſibly, That might proceed from miſinformation, but This muſt needs be too much his owne. All this ado, he ſayes, is but <hi>for the bearing up of Prelates tailes, for the execution of the</hi> Mandamus <hi>of Biſhops.</hi> Might he not as well have ſaid, in caſe hee had thought ſo (which I hardly beleeve he doth,) That all this adoe was, upon a miſapprehenſion; That <hi>Regall power</hi> in a Chriſtian Monarchy cannot well ſtand without <hi>Epiſcopall?</hi> which if it bee indeed a miſapprehenſion, it aroſe not from Biſhops: This knowne axiome, <hi>No Biſhop, no King,</hi> was not invented by a Biſhop. Neither was he a Biſhop, but a States-man and a Iudge, and a witty man in his time, who adviſed King <hi>Iames;</hi> by all meanes you muſt keepe up the Biſhops, becauſe it is written; <hi>Mutato ſacerdotio, mutabifer lex,</hi> Heb. 7.12. <hi>The Prieſthood being changed, there muſt follow of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity a change alſo of the Law:</hi> So hee in alluſion to that Text. But for your ſelfe, if it were your minde to lay all the blame of this quarrell upon the Biſhops, not taking notice of his Majeſties intereſts, or the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his royall Authority, yet you might have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123918:5"/> given good words. What meane ſuch expreſſions, as theſe? <hi>The luſts, and furies of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>malepert</hi> Canterbury, <hi>effronted impudence, the touch of his Graces panton,</hi> and many like; beſides the perpetuall venome of your ſtile, ever when you have ſaid the worſt you can deviſe, leaving a ſting and ſuſpition in the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders minde, as if ſomewhat worſe might bee ſaid: As here in the Preface, <hi>Men whoſe open profeſsion in their printed books,</hi> beſide ſecret practiſes, <hi>leads to wicked ends, &amp;c.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us, <note place="margin">Eph. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſpeak the truth in love.</hi> But where we finde neither truth nor love, neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable matter, nor charitable ſpeeches; pretend you never ſo much to Gods calling, and revelations, and reformations, and what you pleaſe; this we are ſure of: <note place="margin">Mat. 12.34.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh. Bonus homo de bono theſauro profert bona, malus homo de malo theſauro profert mala.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the things themſelves; you have put together here a long beadroll of untruths, purpoſely to raiſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whereof you bring no proofe at all; and therefore you are faine to lubricate them with ſome oyle of Rhetorick, to make them ſlip the better. A long ſcheme of interrogations you put us here: who did this? and, who did that? To all which, conſidering I ſay, you bring no proofe, in reaſon, and equity, you can expect no other returne from us, then a plaine negation: <note place="margin">Quintilian. Decl. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Sat erit, verbo negare, quod verbo ponitur: remove hanc ſpem eludendae menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio civitatis.</hi> Now then I tell you, point by point: It is not He, that hath <hi>kept the King at a distance from your countrey, theſe many yeares.</hi> Not he that <hi>hinders Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> nor that <hi>breaks up Parliaments.</hi> It is not by his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123918:6"/> 
                  <hi>connivence</hi> that the <hi>idolatrous Chappels of both the Queenes are ſo gorgeous and ſo much frequented.</hi> It is not by <hi>his tolerance</hi> that <hi>Maſſe-Prieſts are ſo much multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in City and Countrey.</hi> Hee ſets up no <hi>Cloyſters for Monks and Nuns:</hi> No <hi>Houſes for open Maſſe,</hi> in any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Kings Dominions. Hee holds no <hi>correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Pope.</hi> Hee ſends no <hi>Agents to Rome:</hi> Entertaines not his <hi>Holineſſe Nuncios, here in State.</hi> Hee hindred not our <hi>Alliance with the Swedes &amp; French,</hi> for the relief of <hi>Germany.</hi> He withheld not <hi>from the poore Prince the King of</hi> Bohemiah <hi>to his dying day all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable helpe from Brittaine. Prague</hi> was loſt, and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate</hi> ſurpriſed while hee was yet but a private Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> And what could he doe withall? Hee ſent not <hi>thoſe young Princes</hi> into the Field the other yeare, <hi>ſo poorely provided that one ſilly Commander beat them both.</hi> Hee moved not <hi>that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Prince to ſuch ſtrange Counſell, as now the World ſpeakes of.</hi> Hee betrayed <hi>neither his purpoſe nor his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> King. Hee is not the <hi>prime Authour</hi> of the <hi>Scottiſh broyles.</hi> All this you put upon him; all this wee deny: Whereof ſome things are falſe in themſelves; All in regard of him. And you have not onely truſted <hi>report</hi> too farre, which is ever <note n="q" place="margin">Tertul. Ap.</note> 
                  <hi>Nomen incerti, detrahons, adiiciens, demutans de veritate;</hi> But withall yeelded your ſelfe too much, to that naughty diſpoſition, which they call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a rejoycing in another mans evill: for wee may reaſonably thinke, what ever of all this bee found falſe, you could wiſh it were true: Otherwiſe it is ſtrange, a man ſhould rake together all the diſaſters and miſchiefs, that have been done at home and abroad theſe many yeares, and lay
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123918:6"/> them all upon Him; but not give him the leaſt ſhare in any good action. What good my L. of <hi>Canterbury</hi> hath done in the civill ſtate, what in the Church, what in Citie and Countrey, what in the Univerſity, there will be a time to remember. And though in this diſtempered ſtate of things, <hi>ſeu benè, ſeu malè facta juxtà premunt;</hi> good and bad actions beare a like conſtruction, with many men at leaſt: yet the inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable ſtrength of vertue and innocencie by Gods Bleſſing will overcome at laſt, <note place="margin">Matth. 11.19.</note> and <hi>wiſdome be Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of her children.</hi> In the meane while it ſhall be ſufficient, to ſay to you here that of S. <note n="r" place="margin">Cont: Ruff.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierome: Non eſt neceſſe, ut in tractatihus eccleſiasticis rem tribunalem ventilemus.</hi> It is no way requiſite, that diſputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout points of religion, we ſhould mingle therewith, civill or criminall accuſations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>8 Comming up to your Work, you tell us, you will prove theſe men, againſt whom you informe, to be guilty of <hi>groſſe Arminianiſme, plaine Popery,</hi> and of ſetting up <hi>barbarous Tyranny. Tot Calones quot Milites,</hi> every ſoldier muſt have his Cullion; every ſubſtantive an Epithet put to it, to carry along the Luggage of your Notion: not Popery onely but <hi>plaine Popery,</hi> not Arminianiſme onely but <hi>groſſe Arminianiſme,</hi> nor Tyranny onely but ſetting up of <hi>barbarous Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny:</hi> yet leſt we ſhould be forgetfull or inobſervant of this your great undertaking, you tell it us over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe, and againe; foure times, before you can end; And with it ſhut up this your zealous Preface. But theſe your vehement exaggerations, your long and ſweet Rhetorications, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with which you would charme our Nobles,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123918:7"/> not to ſtirre a weapon againſt you in ſo innocent a Cauſe, I willingly permitt you: Onely two things I muſt expoſtulate with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>9 Firſt, that in caſe you faile in this great buſineſſe, you are content, you ſay, to be cenſured of <note n="*" place="margin">Jf J faile in my faire underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, let me be condemned of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity, and no houre of your leiſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie:</hi> and will never deſire men <hi>to imploy their leaſure any more in hearing your Complaints.</hi> This indeed would be a great deale of Charity on our parts: for it was written of old, <hi>An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth.</hi> Make good your undertaking, prove theſe men guilty of Idolatry, Hereſie, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the King into the Bondage of Popery, the ſubject into a Condition of ſlavery; and their goods, their Bodies, their Lives will be too little ſatisfaction: nay what extreame hazards many have runne already, without any forme of Iuſtice, upon your bare ſuggeſtions, is ſufficiently knowne: now you demand Iuſtice upon my Lo. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where in Caſe you faile of your proofe, ſhall it bee ſufficient for you to ſuffer in point of reputation; and to bee Condemned of Temerity, ſuch a <hi>Lucifuga,</hi> as your ſelfe, an Exploratour of other mens diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whoſe onely Artifice it is, <hi>benè dicta ſeciùs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretari?</hi> I except againſt your iniquitie in this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>10. The other thing is: you complaine of the obſtinate ſilence of the <hi>Engliſh Divines: it is moſt prodigious, you ſay, and one of the Wonders of the World how at this Time they can be ſo dumbe.</hi> You have ſcored downe in your Index here about twenty <hi>Engliſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> that have written within theſe few yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Papiſts and Schiſmatiques, as the neceſſities of the Church did require. God be thanked; there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123918:7"/> was never greater plenty of men, able and willing to encounter our adverſaries on the right hand, or on the left. And do you finde ſo great a ſolitude of <hi>Engliſh Divines,</hi> that you are faine to ſupply your ſelfe with <hi>Burton, Baſtwick, Prinne, Layton, Lilborne;</hi> of whom <hi>Burton</hi> only is the Divine, <hi>Prin</hi> a Lawyer, <hi>Baſtwick</hi> &amp; <hi>Layton</hi> Phyſitians, <hi>Lilborne</hi> a Tradeſman. Are theſe your Engliſh Divines? do you propound theſe for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itable Examples to the Clergie of this Kingdome?</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Depuduit, profugúſque pudor, ſua ſigna reliquit.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>You call us to the Example of thoſe <hi>Marian Dayes, Times of hotteſt Perſecution:</hi> as if now were the Time for <hi>faithfull Witneſſes</hi> to ſtand up in defence of true Religion: That is, to oppoſe thoſe Lawes now by which Popery was then caſt out: to condemne that Liturgie, and thoſe Ceremonies, as ſuperſtitious now, which were then ordained to cut off ſuperſtition: and the retaining of which, our very <note n="a" place="margin">Iſta autem multaque alia ex moribus &amp; caeremoniis antiquis, politicorum ſuaſu, contra hujus novi cleri volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Regina retinuit, &amp;c. Et certe fecit plurimum ad ſtabilitatem, firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatemque haereſeos, &amp;c. Sander. de ſchiſm. Angl.</note> adverſaries cannot but Confeſſe, hath beene the ſtrongeſt ſinew and ſupport of our Reformation. To revile Biſhops now, that were then prime Martyrs: as if their very calling were wicked, to whom even <note n="b" place="margin">Scio inſtaurationem eccleſiae Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae &amp; everſionem Papiſmi, poſt Deum &amp; Reges, deberi praecipue Epiſcoporum doctrinae &amp; induſtriae: Quorum etiam nonnulli martyrio, &amp;c. Pet. Moli n. Ep. 3.</note> Strangers give this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie: that they were then the Chief Inſtruments of plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pure Religion among us, and have beene of conſerving it ever ſince. We muſt be mad now, and cut off our right hand with our left, or elſe <hi>England is gone off,</hi> you ſay, <hi>from her zeale to the true Religion.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:123918:8"/> But leave this wicked vanitie, Mocke not God, the World, and your owne Conſcience. Doe not paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell perſons and things ſo extreamly different; <note place="margin">Prov. 17.15.</note> 
                  <hi>to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Wicked, and condemne the juſt, are both Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <p>11. In your firſt Chapter; you ſeeme to ſeare the World is miſtaken in your Quarrell, and doth not underſtand it to be ſo extenſive as it is, being as you ſay, not only that which <note n="a" place="margin">P. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>properly concerneth your ſelves, but that which rubbeth upon other Churches;</hi> not <hi>the Booke, Canons, and Epiſcopacie</hi> only; but many <hi>notable wrongs and affronts openly done to the reformed Religion.</hi> Experience teacheth us to underſtand your meaning; <note n="b" place="margin">P, 12.</note> you found <hi>in your generall aſſembly, you ſay, the cockle of Arminianiſme comming up apace in many furrowes of your field; which being cast over the dyke, it was at once received and replanted in England in too good a ſoyle.</hi> Were it ſo; truly you have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it ſo faſt into that good ſoyle, that it is likely to take no very deepe roote: though how it has beene <hi>received</hi> or <hi>replanted</hi> here, I know not; except it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you, that your expulſed Biſhops and Clergie were permitted fire and water, or ſo much as lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood among us. But we aske not, <hi>quo Warranto,</hi> by what Authority you take upon you this large Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſet right the Church of England. Nor are we very ſolicitous to informe our ſelves of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of your quarrell. This we are ſure of, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The end and beginning of Buſineſse appeares not together,</hi> eſpecially of Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Prov. 17.14.</note> is like the <hi>letting out of Water,</hi> it will not alwayes ſtop where men think.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:123918:8"/>
               <p>But whereas you are ſo charitable to judge <note n="*" place="margin">P. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Biſhops of the Iſle to be innocent and very free of theſe Miſchiefs, and ſuch as would readily purge themſelves, if only my Lord of Canterbury and his dependants were in any way to receive from the Kings juſtice ſome part of their Deſervings:</hi> Herein we cannot but challenge you of injuſtice, that ſome of them being innocent, you would make it the Concluding vote of your Booke, that all without exception ſhould be rid away. Will you <hi>deſtroy the righteous with the wicked?</hi> But yet your charity we are readie to compenſate; and tell you, we believe there are involved in the Covenant many honeſt Hearts, many well meaning Soules: and that they are not all ſo blame-worthy, as you their <hi>ſpirituall Miſleaders</hi> are; nay we believe, divers of them, were they truly taught the nature of this Action you have put them into, would gladly purge themſelves, and leave you <hi>to receive from the King's Iuſtice ſome part of your deſerving.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>12. You have brought us next a long Syllogiſme, which is to be the touchſtone of your whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and ſummarily is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">P. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoever in the Kings Dominions ſpreads abroad Poperie, or any Doctrine oppoſite to the Religion and Lawes of the Land, now eſtabliſhed; ought to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Canterbury</hi> and his <hi>Dependants</hi> have ſpread abroad in the Kings Dominions, Doctrines oppoſite to our Religion and Lawes; and eſpecially Points of groſſeſt Popery. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where I hope you will give me Leave to ſcruple two or three things without Offence: and firſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123918:9"/> touching your <hi>Major:</hi> Let me tell you, it is ever a lurching Tricke to Complicate many Termes in one Propoſition; as here be two: <hi>Spreading abroad Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie,</hi> and <hi>ſpreading abroad any Doctrine oppoſite to the Lawes eſtabliſhed.</hi> It is a Fallacie <hi>Multarum Quaestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> to which the Reſpondent cannot very adviſedly give his Anſwere at once: for it may be halfe true, and halfe falſe. Know then, one you muſt leave out, by the Law of Art, unleſſe you will affirm them to be both one, or convertible, which I thinke you will not. Let me Counſell you then to leave out the Word <hi>Poperie,</hi> and that becauſe it is an Ambiguous Word; about which you and your Oppoſites are very little agreed, and in all Controverſies, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Principium eſt Nomen.</hi> Firſt you muſt agree upon the Cleare Meaning of your Terms, or elſe inſtead of Diſputing you will but beate the Ayre. As heere in this Caſe, you will urge them with ſome Doctrines and call them <hi>Poperie:</hi> They will acknowledge the Doctrines, but deny the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery:</hi> then you muſt revert to diſpute, what is Popery, a thing that by all reaſon ſhould have beene cleared at firſt. You ſeeme to define it by <hi>Tenets of Reformed Churches,</hi> and <hi>Tenets of reformed Divines;</hi> as if what croſſeth theſe, were <hi>Poperie.</hi> But this is to define it by uncertainties: for Churches differ in their Tenets, not to goe from home, <note n="*" place="margin">P. 98.</note> you tell us <hi>you could never in Scotland be induced to follow ſo much of the Maſſe as we retained in England.</hi> Divines differ in their Tenets. What thing more knowne? He that followes not <hi>Calvin</hi> in the Point of <hi>Praedeſtination,</hi> may yet fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Melancthon.</hi> And he a man, (as <note n="a" place="margin">Pietas or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:123918:9"/> very truly ſaith) never a whit inferiour to him. Shall the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be <hi>Poperie?</hi> that will not be univerſally true, for there was a Time when S. <hi>Paul</hi> commended both: their <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith</hi> and <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Obedience.</hi> Shall the Cuſtomes and uſages of that Church be Poperie? not all. For they had many in Common with the whole <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> which cannot without great ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and falſhood be taxed of <hi>Poperie.</hi> You of all men have made this word <hi>Poperie,</hi> ſuch an ambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory word, that we know not where to fixe it. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme ſhall be Poperie, if you pleaſe to call it ſo: to refuſe the oathes of allegeance and ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſhall not be Poperie, if you pleaſe not to call it ſo. Our <hi>Engliſh liturgie</hi> with you is a Popiſh maſſe; our <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Popiſh ceremonies. Now ſhould your adverſaries be ſo unadviſed to grant themſelves pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable, for teaching and maintaining <hi>Popery,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it ever in your acception? In the meane while, to ſay, they are puniſhable, for teaching any doctrine <hi>oppoſite to the Religion by Law eſtabliſhed;</hi> is to ſay a Conſequent, and undeniable truth, which will they, or nill they, they muſt ſubmit to. Now then let this undefined thing <hi>Poperie</hi> ſtand by; or elſe let every Doctrine inſiſted on by you, be Popiſh ſo, as withall oppoſite to the Religion by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: and therein you ſhall do very well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>12. Next, in your <hi>Minor:</hi> I may not ſuffer you to jumpe out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Scotland;</hi> as you do in this Clauſe of it: <hi>Our Religion and Lawes.</hi> Ours? whoſe? yours, in <hi>Scotland?</hi> ſhall theſe men, ſubjects of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and Members of this Church, be puniſhable,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123918:10"/> for teaching ſome Doctrine oppoſite to the Religion by Law eſtabliſhed in <hi>Scotland?</hi> when did they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to your Religion or Lawes? you <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scota ante aliquot Annos Anglorum Auxilus è ſervitute Gallica liberati, Religionis Cultui &amp; Ritibus cum Anglis Communibus ſubſcripſerunt.</hi> The ſcotiſh being ſome yeares before delivered from the ſlavery of the French by the Aydes of the Engliſh, ſubſcribed to the ſame Worſhip and Rite of Religion, which the Engliſh uſed. <hi>Buchan: hiſt. Scot. l.</hi> 19.</note> have ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to ours, as coy as you are of us now: we to yours never. And yet would you candidly ſet out even your own Lawes; happily they would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe you upon them. But if you ſuperinduce the <hi>Bookes of Diſcipline,</hi> or Records, to them utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, <note n="y" place="margin">Large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar. p. 270</note> wonderfully preſerved, and now after a long ſilence of Time, no doubt, as uncorruptly exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by you: if that muſt be a <hi>Canon</hi> to regulate your Church and Religion; then they will recoile, and deſire to be tryed by their owne Lawes. The ſumme of all, is: they would not have you juggle and ſophiſticate, confound and tumble together Places, Perſons, Things, as every where you do; to raiſe Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, not to diſcover Truth. In all Equity then, this muſt be your ſyllogiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoever in the Kings Dominions, reſpectively, ſpreads abroad any Doctrine oppoſite to the Religion by Lawes eſtabliſhed; ought to be puniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Canterburie</hi> and his <hi>Dependents,</hi> being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>England,</hi> have ſpread abroad Doctrines op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to The Religion, by Lawes eſtabliſhed in <hi>England.</hi> Ergo.</p>
               <p>Now if you can acquite your ſelfe of this <hi>Minor</hi> and carry it handſomly through your whole Booke, you will doe a memorable perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. But you meane no ſuch thing: and therefore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123918:10"/> I deſire the Reader to do it for you; upon every point to bring you to this teſt: which he muſt do if he will be juſt and impartiall. For make you up your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as you pleaſe, with reformed Divines and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Preachers; that wil be but to call up againſt you other orthodoxe Preachers; and all to no purpoſe: for nothing is puniſhable but by Law: <hi>Simul ac a jure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſeris,</hi> go you from that, and either in Fact or Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, men wil think they may uſe a moderate liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <p>13 Firſt, touching <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> in relation to Fact: It is but hard meaſure in you to repreſent it preſently with this <hi>Odium: A</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>dangerous inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and ſuch a one as was found to be the readiest Engin, which had ever beene uſed by the Pope or</hi> Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard <hi>to overthrow the Church and State of</hi> Holland. For were this true, yet ſure it could bee true by no other neceſſity, then as <hi>Medicus cantat;</hi> a Phyſitian may be skilfull in ſong, but it is no intrinſecall act of his Profeſſion. An <hi>Arminian</hi> may bee a ſeditious Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, but it flowes not from any of the <hi>five diſputed points.</hi> Divines may differ about the order of Gods <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> and yet bee good ſubjects to their Prince: In the meane while, your ſelfe that make this objection, living in a <hi>Monarchicall State,</hi> make no bones to affirme; <note n="*" place="margin">Poſtſcrip. p. 14.</note> That <hi>publike Aſſemblies, and Conventions may bee held without the authority of the Civill Magiſtrate:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. p. 8.</note> That, <hi>ſubjects may beare Armes againſt their Soveraigne:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">p. 14.</note> That, <hi>there is and ought to bee in a Kingdome, an Eccleſiaſtique Power, ſupreme in it ſelfe, and independent on the King.</hi> Theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touch the life of a State, and tend dangerouſly to the diſſolution of Government; yet theſe muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123918:11"/> be borne with, in you: but if men doubt of abſolute Reprobation, or ſticke at any like rigid Doctrine, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the State muſt looke about, it is ſome ſecret Plot to <hi>betray the Kingdome to the Pope or Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ultra Sauromatas fugere hinc libet, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>I take not upon me to Apologize for <hi>Arminians:</hi> let them ſtand or fall by themſelves: But I thinke a dramme of equity will obtaine them thus much, that they may bee as good and loyall ſubjects in any State or Kingdome, as they which maintaine your aforeſaid poſitions or any of them. When my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that then was, tooke ſo much care (as you tell us) to ſuppreſſe <hi>Barrow</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and to enact his <hi>Lambethane</hi> Articles (which you ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly call the <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Synod of Lambeth</hi>) the Queene, even <note n="*" place="margin">Preſat.</note> 
                  <hi>that moſt ſacred Queene Elizabeth,</hi> did not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it as any great ſervice done to the State, or as if the Kingdome had been thereby ſecured: Which is plaine enough by the cold thankes ſhee gave him. If you know not the carriage of that buſineſſe, I pray you informe your ſelfe better, out of the ſtory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>14. The greateſt Accuſation that lies againſt my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> here, in this matter of <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> is the <hi>preferment of men</hi> whom you ſuſpect to encline to the opinions of <hi>Arminius,</hi> wherein before you paſſe any Verdict, you ſhould doe well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider: Firſt, whether all <hi>Preferments</hi> be ſo abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his <hi>Graces</hi> diſpoſing, that hee may bee truely ſaid to preferre them all. Secondly, whether hee looke upon them in that Quality, as they encline to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123918:11"/> ſuch Opinions, and bee not obliged to favour them, for ſome other eminent Abilities, or Merit of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſervice, done in Church or State. Thirdly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome others ſufficiently known to be <hi>anti-Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> be not as high in the Church, &amp; as well promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as they. Fourthly, whether moſt men promoted in the Church, are not upon your own falſe grounds, by you cauſeleſly ſuſpected to be <hi>Arminians. Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid horum tetigeris, Ulcus est:</hi> you are not Proofe in any of theſe. And becauſe the Preferments of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry men may bee upon ſundry motives, by ſundry Meanes and Procurements: Nor can it be any thing elſe in you, but an invidious Preſumption to thinke all done by his <hi>Grace</hi> in favour of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> whereas all in that kinde is not done by him, nor any with an eye of favour upon <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> clamour while you pleaſe, my Anſwer is this: and it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſatisfie any honeſt man. There is no man, promoted in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Lord of <hi>Canterburies</hi> helpe, but ſubſcribes to the <hi>Articles;</hi> the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of this Church. Now theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> either they condemne the Opinions of <hi>Arminius,</hi> or they doe not: If they doe not, then is <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> either a thing ſet by, and left at liberty, neither belongs it to my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or any other truſted with the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, to take cogniſance of any mans judgement in thoſe points: Or if thoſe Points bee comprehended in the <hi>Articles</hi> and not condemned, belike they are approved there: But if the <hi>Articles</hi> doe condemne <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> all men promoted in the Church ſubſcribe to the <hi>Articles:</hi> They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123918:12"/> 
                  <hi>fully and heartily to aſſent to the Doctrine there ſet downe;</hi> which Profeſſion is as <hi>valid,</hi> as an oath; and an <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Oath for confirmation is an end of all ſtrife.</hi> So that to affirme his <hi>Grace</hi> keepes a conſtant courſe, in promoting <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> as a Sect offenſive to this Church, is but a meere calumny: Their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription being as great and apparant a Purgation of any their adherence to heterodox Opinions, as they can poſſibly exhibit, or hee require of them: And ſhould he require more, he could not juſtifie it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <p>15. That which brought up Arminianiſme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, was, you ſay, <note n="*" place="margin">P. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>a gentle ayre from Court:</hi> which were it true, as it is undoubtedly falſe, yet it leaves no reall Aſperſion upon thoſe Opinions. The Court does not alwayes cheriſh the evill ſeeds: it is the voice of <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> ſometimes; <note n="a" place="margin">Optat. l. 1. Aug. Ep. 48.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis cum palatio?</hi> The <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did often complaine they were borne downe by <hi>favour at Court;</hi> and ſo do you now, and ſo did alwayes all unquiet Spirits, when they could not have there, what themſelves deſired. <note n="*" place="margin">P. 11.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wederburne,</hi> you tell us, was made Biſhop of <hi>Dunblane, and that Biſhop is alwayes Deane of the Chappell Royall: and a ſociety of twenty foure Chaplaines was erected, the fitteſt that could be found in the whole Kingdome, to preach to the State the Deanes Arminian Tenets.</hi> Where, it may be, all the offence is, that your ſelfe was none of the number.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <p>16. Paſſing over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> you queſtion there: <note n="*" place="margin">P. 15. P. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Who holds downe the head of that Orthodoxe Primate?</hi> Which complaint, after three or foure pages, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume againe, thus. <hi>What fray, makes that worthy Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:123918:12"/> Vſher <hi>to foretell oft to his friends his expectation, to be ſent over ſea, to die a Pedant, teaching boyes for his bread, by the perſecution of this faction.</hi> Where this ſtrange expreſſion from your pen, <hi>Orthodoxe Primate,</hi> made me almoſt forget the maine of your complaint. For ſay, in good earneſt, is <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> a wicked and Antichriſtian calling? So you teach ſometimes. And ſure if a <hi>ſimple Biſhop</hi> be a limb of Antichriſt, a <hi>Primate</hi> muſt be a very principall member: how then, <hi>Orthodoxe primate?</hi> Or, why care you, who holds downe his head? Were it in your power, would you advance it? You that have howted all Eccleſiaſticall Dignities quite out of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? You tell us plainly, that a totall ejection of the Biſhops <note n="*" place="margin">Poſtſcrip. p. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>would much increaſe the joy and proſperity of all the three dominions:</hi> We have juſt reaſon to think then, that if this <hi>Orthodoxe Primate</hi> were in your Power, you would divide betwixt his <hi>Orthodoxie,</hi> and his <hi>Primacie,</hi> by ſuch a kind of diſtinction, as that was of old; <note n="b" place="margin">Platin. in vit. Ioan. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Gibellinorum, bona Guelfa;</hi> the <hi>Man</hi> might be <hi>Orthodoxe,</hi> but the <hi>Primacie,</hi> with what belongs to it, his Rents and Revenues, would be found all <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> ſo that he muſt be content indeed to <hi>die a Pedant, teaching boyes for his bread.</hi> But to the maine of your Complaint, take his Anſwer, which upon ſight of this paſſage in your booke, he made with his owne mouth. <hi>This is notoriouſly falſe, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid any ſuch thing, I never thought it; and I am in my particular beholding to my Lord of Canterbury.</hi> I had the happineſſe to be by, when my <hi>Lord Primate</hi> ſpake this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <p>17. Your aptneſſe to miſconſtrue even the beſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123918:13"/> actions, appeares by the cenſure you put upon His Majeſties <hi>Declaration before the Articles.</hi> You make it but a crafty trick in his <hi>Grace,</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by the Duke his Patron,</hi> you ſay, to perſwade that courſe of ſilence purpoſely to give <note n="*" place="margin">Their crafty leader ſeeing the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſinding it meet a little to hold in, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 19.</note> advantage to the <hi>Arminians.</hi> It were a happy thing, if in all emergent controverſies men would carrie themſelves with that temper, and prudence, as that no ſuch declarations might be needfull: But when the fire of contention begins to burne, and endanger the peace of Church and State; it is then time for Kings, who are <hi>nutritii Eccleſiae,</hi> to interpoſe their power and ſuppreſſe the flame. What our gracious Soveraigne did, was done <hi>more majorum,</hi> after the example of all godly Princes. In the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the elder, every mans tongue ran upon the <hi>Trinity,</hi> nothing could be heard but perpetuall wrangling about thoſe high myſteries; whereupon that pious Prince forbad all diſputing thereabout, <note n="c" place="margin">Sozom. l. 7. c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>latâ lege &amp; paenâ conſtitutâ.</hi> Had you lived then, you would have ſaid; This was but the tricke of ſome Prelate, to give advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the <hi>Sabellians, Photinians, Arrians,</hi> and the like. In theſe very queſtions <hi>bleſſed King Iames</hi> both counſelled and approved a pacificatory edict, deviſed and publiſhed in <hi>Holland,</hi> to make peace there; which indeed was variouſly carped at. But God forbid, that at ſuch exigences, for the miſpriſion of ſome diſaffected ſpirits, Kings and Princes ſhould lay by their care; whoſe office it is to ſuppreſſe <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi> in <hi>Church,</hi> as well as <hi>theft, homicide, or like crimes in State,</hi> as <note n="d" place="margin">Ep. 50. &amp; cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. 3. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tels us. But what advantage did the <hi>Arminians</hi> make of this edict, I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123918:13"/> pray? Yes, <note n="*" place="margin">P. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Many Doctors,</hi> you ſay, <hi>in both Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and over all the Land, boldly gave out their minde to all they met with, for the advancement of the new way. Boldly gave out their minde?</hi> But did they print as boldly? I am ſure ſome of the contrary part as boldly gave out their mindes: otherwiſe your intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence had not been ſo good. And what know you, but that many books, like to be offenſive in this kinde, were and are ſuppreſſed by my Lord of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburies</hi> care? I am ſure, you can keepe no tale of them, no more than <hi>Diagoras</hi> his friend could of thoſe that were drowned; <hi>quia nuſquam picti ſunt,</hi> for they appeare not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <p>18. Needs will you make the world believe; in this quarrell of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries</hi> Predeceſſour, Archbiſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> was <hi>ſo farre</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">P. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>wrought out of grace with the King, that he remained ſome yeares before his death, well neare confined to his houſe at Lambeth:</hi> and that for the ſame cauſe, is <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged up in the Tower that great and learned Biſhop of Lincolne.</hi> Where touching the firſt; in good time ſaid you, <hi>well neare</hi> confined: For certainly, no other confinement lay upon him at <hi>Lambeth</hi> ſome yeares before his death, but by that which ſerves an arreſt upon all the ſonnes of men, <hi>age</hi> and <hi>infirmity.</hi> And for the ſecond, that <hi>Arminianiſme</hi> is any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in my Lord of <hi>Lincolnes</hi> affaire, is more than I ever underſtood; or, I believe, any man elſe. It were a great folly for me to miſreport or diſſemble in things ſo publike and notorious as theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <p>19. Much adoe you make about <hi>Chounes</hi> Booke: where you begin with the <hi>Licenſe,</hi> but miſtake the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123918:14"/> 
                  <hi>Licenſer;</hi> whence I hope we may conclude, you are over-apt to truſt <hi>flying Report.</hi> For, had you uſed ocular inſpection here, we cannot but think you can read a printed Name. Touching the Booke it ſelfe, very eager you are to ſtretch all to the worſt. For, he ſaith not, <hi>Fides, Reſipiſcentia, Perſeverantia,</hi> Faith, Repentance, Perſeverance, <hi>are the Cauſes of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as you alledge: but <hi>Fidei, Reſipiſcentiae, Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae</hi> recta <hi>quae est ex Deo</hi> Ordinatio: Kenne you no difference here, betwixt mans act, in believing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, and perſevering; and Gods <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, faith, repentance, and perſeverance, to be the meanes of ſalvation. But a dangerous matter it is, to fall into the hands of a Man, that is reſolved to make the worſt of every thing he meets with. You tell us farther, D. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> in the Face of the <hi>Starre-Chamber,</hi> charged my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> with this Booke. That he did not neither; in the <hi>High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> ſomewhat hee wrangled about <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls:</hi> which truly was not worth the writing into <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But more than all this; <hi>It wounds,</hi> you ſay, <hi>the Kings Monarchick Government at the very heart, and transferres from the Crowne to the Miter one of its fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Diamonds; which the King and His Father before him did ever love moſt dearely.</hi> You cite not the Words, nor the place: but in your Chapter of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie,</hi> we cannot miſſe it, ſure. There he is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſay; that <note n="*" place="margin">P. 113.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings and Princes are accompted ſonnes of the Church, That Biſhops make Canons, which yet have their Vivacity, or Act of life from Kings, as the Heads.</hi> This is all in effect, he ſaith there. I wonder
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123918:14"/> much what deſigne M. <hi>Choune,</hi> a Lay-Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhould have, to transferre from the <hi>Crowne</hi> to the <hi>Miter</hi> this faire Diamond, <hi>Supremacie in Cauſes Eccleſiaſticall:</hi> for that is it you meane: And I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der more to finde you ſo jealous of it. But be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, good Sir, neither M. <hi>Choune</hi> nor the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any ſuch theft. In the meane while, <note place="margin">Rom. 2.21.</note> 
                  <hi>thou that teacheſt a man ſhould not ſteale, doſt thou ſteale?</hi> Doe not you with open face rob the <hi>Crowne</hi> of this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and transferre it to your Eccleſiaſticke Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies? <note n="f" place="margin">Parall. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor</hi> ſayes you doe; And in your Poſtſcript-anſwer to him here, durſt you deny it, ſo much as in one ſyllable? Are you not faine to conclude the point with him thus, <hi>Our Prince is very well content from the Generall Aſſembly,</hi> the higheſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticke Court, <hi>ſhould come no appeale at all to him?</hi> Belike, from other Seſſions and Presbyteries, lies Appeale thither, but there you are at the top: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Looke no higher, then: though ſure the <hi>top</hi> is ever the Kings by right. <hi>Obediunt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul &amp; regnant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Choune.</hi> Princes <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> but <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>governe</hi> it withall: but with you, it is ſimply <hi>obediunt,</hi> nay <note n="g" place="margin">Synodo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſint, non ut regnent, ſed ut ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, &amp;c. Bez. conf. c. 5. art. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſerviunt,</hi> by no meanes, <hi>reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> You may make Acts, cenſure, depoſe, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and <hi>no Appeale</hi> lies from you. Indeed you ſlide it over with a mannerly expreſſion, <hi>our Prince is very well content,</hi> &amp;c. but ſhould the Biſhops build up ſuch an <hi>independent Supremacie,</hi> and be queſtioned for it, would it ſuffice for them to anſwer, <hi>Our Prince is very well content?</hi> That <hi>perſonate Ieſuite,</hi> as you call him, objects; you deny Kings, <hi>Power to convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Aſſemblies:</hi> whereto you anſwer; <note n="*" place="margin">Poſtſcr. p. 14</note> 
                  <hi>he knowes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123918:15"/> the contrary, that you give to all Chriſtian Soveraignes, ſo much intereſt in affaires of the Church, as to convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Aſſemblies when and where they pleaſe: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, you hold indeed, that without them, you may convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate your ſelves, in ſome caſe.</hi> So tender you are of preſerving in the <hi>Crowne,</hi> that faire Diamond: And ſo much you indigne at <hi>Choune,</hi> though very inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent thereof, that hee ſhould transferre it to the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> the fault is, he did not indeed transferre it to the <hi>Presbytery.</hi> Where bee it knowne, That <hi>Eccleſiaſtick power</hi> is not to bee leſſened by the expulſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; now it is <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> but then it ſhall bee <hi>diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <p>21. In your third Chapter you <note n="*" place="margin">P. 31.</note> taxe my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> for promoving Maſter <hi>Duries</hi> Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation with the Churches beyond Sea. This <hi>Durie</hi> is a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Miniſter, that hath much pained himſelfe, travelling up and downe <hi>Germany,</hi> to ſolicit an Vnion betwixt the Churches of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> confeſſion, and the reſt. My Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> found his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour, <hi>Archbiſhop Abbot,</hi> imbarqued in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne; and thereupon inclined the rather, to give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to it: but ever kept himſelfe within the bounds, which his Predeceſſour had ſet. Now if this be a fault, there be many partakers: For wee are made beleeve, few Ambaſſadours, or Agents in thoſe parts, few Doctours or Profeſſors of their Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, that have not intermedled more or leſſe, to promove this action. But after all; I doubt, you need not much feare the ſucceſſe. A <hi>ſynctetiſme</hi> you ſay, <hi>all good men did ever pant for; but not a full peace.</hi> I ſuppoſe you meane, <hi>they ſhould combine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123918:15"/> the common enemy, but ſtill keepe at oddes amongst themſelves.</hi> Yet a <hi>ſyncretiſme</hi> being not every daies Word, you might have done well to explaine your ſelfe better: and the rather, becauſe the <hi>Cretians</hi> had an ill name, you know, for cheating and cozening, that poſſibly <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, may bee taken in a vicious ſenſe; <hi>to pack together for miſchiefe.</hi> And I thinke, <hi>Beza</hi> uſes it ſo, in an Epiſtle of his to Biſhop <hi>Grindall. Quis porrò fuerit quorundam nuper adverſus omnes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Partium, ac proinde etiam adverſus Gallicas &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras quoque Eccleſias, quas omnes nobiſcum in omnibus doctriae capitibus conſentire arbitramur, conatus &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>jam pridem ad vos uſque perlatum eſſe Opinor. Conatus, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: I hope, this is not the <hi>ſyncretiſme,</hi> you have long panted for. But a <hi>ſyncretiſme</hi> you would have, not a <hi>full peace;</hi> though otherwiſe a man <hi>very peaceably minded.</hi> Now wee in <hi>England,</hi> are taught to pray thus; That God would <hi>inſpire continually his univerſall Church, with the ſpirit of truth, unity, and concord: and grant, that</hi> not onely, Theſe, and Thoſe: <hi>but even all they, that confeſſe his holy name, may agree in the truth of his holy word, and live in unity and godly love.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <p>22. And thus much of <hi>Fact,</hi> now to matter of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>Opinion;</hi> wherein all that is objected will be found, as hitherto it hath been, lighter then vanity it ſelfe. But when ſuch things as theſe are printed with Licence, and informed of as matters of very great conſequence; wee truſt it will bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, if wee loſe a little time, to give ſome anſwer at leaſt, to ſuch an <hi>importunate Delatour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <p>23. In the point of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> one paſſage is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123918:16"/> ſaid to bee gotten from his <hi>Graces</hi> Pen: And that is, the changing of a <hi>Clauſe</hi> in the <hi>Collect,</hi> for the Queen and the Royall Iſſue: inſtead of <hi>Father of thine Elect and their ſeed,</hi> putting in, <hi>the Fountaine of all goodneſſe. Grave Crimen, Cai Caeſar;</hi> and not ſo fortunate as to ſteale out of the world, but with noiſe enough. For this complaint you tooke up of <hi>Burton.</hi> But you charge it further; It was, ſay you, in <hi>favour of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme, to cut and mangle the very Liturgie of the Church, otherwiſe a ſacred peece in</hi> England, <hi>and a</hi> Noli me tangere, <hi>even in the ſmalleſt points, bee they never ſo much by any cenſured of Errour.</hi> Then which, what could bee ſpoken more ridiculous? For firſt, not to urge how this <hi>Collect</hi> is a <hi>poſt-nate,</hi> to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgie of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Wherein could this Clauſe offend even <hi>Arminius</hi> himſelfe? The difference betwixt him and his Oppoſites, being not, Whether there bee any <hi>Elect</hi> or <hi>none?</hi> or whether God bee the <hi>Father of them</hi> and <hi>their ſeed?</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Election;</hi> whether it be, man <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply conſidered,</hi> or man <hi>ſo qualified,</hi> that is, <hi>beleeving,</hi> and <hi>repenting:</hi> whether <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, or reſult from Gods <hi>Election.</hi> Doth any <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian</hi> deny a <hi>perſonall Election,</hi> that is, an <hi>Election of ſingular perſons,</hi> as you ignorantly ſay here? They hold it to bee indeed, <hi>ſingularium credentium.</hi> But what is that to my Lord of <hi>Canterbury?</hi> or what to this <hi>Clauſe</hi> of the <hi>Collect?</hi> This innocent <hi>Clauſe,</hi> not touching in the leaſt manner the condition or motive of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> why ſhould it be diſcarded in favour of <hi>Arminianiſme?</hi> Againe, if the word <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> did ſcandaline his <hi>Grace,</hi> why did hee not put it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123918:16"/> out of other Collects, as well as out of this as, upon <hi>All Saints</hi> Day, <hi>Almighty God, which haſt knit together thy</hi> Elect <hi>in one Communion,</hi> &amp;c. And at the Buriall of the Dead, <hi>Almighty God, in whom the ſoules of them that are elected,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>accompliſh the number of thine</hi> Elect. Beſides, be you pleaſed to know, your Brethren here in <hi>England</hi> helpe this Prayer with a certaine diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <note n="g" place="margin">Ipſ. Newes.</note> 
                  <hi>Elect to a Crowne temporall, and</hi> Elect <hi>to a Crowne eternall:</hi> doubting that ſomebody at ſome time may be included in it, whom they cannot hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily allow to be one of Gods <hi>Elect.</hi> Now were his <hi>Grace</hi> content to pray with that ſingleneſſe and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of heart as theſe your godly Brethren uſe to do, in caſe this Clauſe were peccant, and would not downe with him (what an eaſie ſcape was there for him?) it had been but to reſerve to himſelfe, that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall meaning of <hi>Elect to a Crowne temporall,</hi> and all had been ſafe. But in charity, I beſeech you, believe the matter to be indeed what it was; when this Change was made, the King had no iſſue. But, ſhy you, <hi>A childleſſe man may ſay in his prayers, that God is the Father of the Elect, and of their ſeed?</hi> Yet, by your favour, not ſo properly then; for to addreſſe a prayer to God under ſuch a compellation, <hi>Father of thine Elect and of their ſeed,</hi> ſhould doubtleſſe in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity relate to the proſperity of the <hi>Kings and Queens Children,</hi> which then were none. For you ſcoffe upon the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of this Church, <hi>a ſacred peece,</hi> and a <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li me tangere in</hi> England. Though you preſume you have gotten the time now, wherein you may ſay any thing of Gods publike Worſhip eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; yet we truſt you will finde your ſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely diſappointed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:123918:17"/>
               <p>24. This is all you can get from his Grace's Pen, to helpe on the clamour here; except that you tell us, you have a ſuſpition, my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> directed, in penning a paſſage of the <hi>large Declaration,</hi> concerning your cenſure at <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow</hi> upon the opinions of <hi>Arminius:</hi> Which were there condemned to be <hi>Popiſh opinions.</hi> For, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Balcanquall,</hi> you ſay, could not relate it; becauſe he was a member of the <hi>Dort Synod.</hi> Who penned, or who directed in penning that Declaration, is to me unknowne; but ſure your reaſon is a meere cobweb. For why may not a Member of the <hi>Dort</hi> Synod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late a matter of Fact, as it paſſed in the Aſſembly at <hi>Glaſgow?</hi> Becauſe your affections do biaſſe you, in all your relations, to your owne party, think you it is ſo with every man elſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <p>25. The hard ſhift you make to finde out ſuch Objections as theſe, are his Graces moſt evident Purgation, and ſo he is cleare in this matter. One thing let me tell you by the Way, you cite King <hi>Iames:</hi> And great reaſon we ſhould riſe up to ſuch a ſacred Authority. And willingly would I hereby ingage you, that K. <hi>Iames</hi> may be cited to you, upon juſt occaſion? It is a Rule in Law: <note n="m" place="margin">Reg. Iur. in Sexto.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod ſemel placuit, amplius diſplicere non debet:</hi> An authority admitted for good here, ſhould not be refuſed elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Shall we decide concerning the maine points which have been, as you pretend, the prime and proper Incentives of this preſent miſerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion. That is, the <hi>Canons, Liturgie, Supremacie of Kings, Epiſcopall Government,</hi> by King <hi>Iames</hi> his ſentence? Who, in many yeares, with much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123918:17"/> Care and Coſt laboured to build up, what at one Commotion you have tumbled downe? was it not <note n="n" place="margin">I, that in the yeare of God 84. erected Biſhops, and depreſſed all their popular Parity, &amp;c. I, that for the ſpace of ſixe yeares before my comming into <hi>England,</hi> laboured no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as to depreſſe their Parity, and re-erect Biſhops againe, &amp;c. That Biſhops ought to be in the Church, I ever maintained as an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike Inſtitution,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</hi> Monit. to all Christ. Monarchs.</note> King <hi>Iames?</hi> But this is always the faſhion of men that are wholly addicted to ſerve their owne Opinions. Let K. <hi>Iames</hi> declare himſelfe in ſome ſpeculative points of ſo abſtruſe a nature, that the moſt acute Iudgements, after long ſearch are faine to ſit downe, with that of the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>! Let him in ſuch points as theſe declare himſelfe in any manner as you deſire; and then who but <hi>King Iames, a venerable Prince?</hi> but if he ſpeake in things practicall and palpable upon long experience and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledneſſe of judgement any thing that croſſeth your Humour; then you turne your deafe eare to King <hi>Iames; Charme he never ſo wiſely,</hi> you will not heare him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <p>26. Now we go on to Popery, where the firſt point objected to my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> is: <hi>That he holds not the Pope to be The Antichriſt.</hi> How know you that? Where hath he told you ſo? <note n="*" place="margin">P. 35</note> You ſay, <hi>he confeſſeth that place of the publike Liturgie wherein it was imported, was changed by his own hand.</hi> How was it changed? From theſe words; <hi>Root out that Babyloniſh and Antichriſtian Sect,</hi> into this forme of words, <hi>Root out that Romiſh and Babyloniſh Sect of them, &amp;c.</hi> So the Word <hi>Antichristian</hi> is delete. A ſtrange Cauſe have you taken in hand, that muſt be thus unhappily defended. Firſt, you are wrong up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Liturgie</hi> againe: This Prayer, is in the Service
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123918:18"/> appointed for the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> which you fraudulently, and to raiſe hatred, call the <hi>publike Liturgie:</hi> The publike Liturgie was extant and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> before that Service was begotten, or the miſerable occaſion of it fell out. Secondly, <note n="*" place="margin">Ep. 2.18.</note> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> tels us, there be <hi>many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists:</hi> ſo that though a man doubt, whether the Pope of Rome be <hi>that great Antichriſt;</hi> yet he may eſteeme well enough the Doctrines and practices of the Romiſh Church to be <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and call them ſo: what needed this blotting of the Service then? His <hi>Grace</hi> might have held his Opinion, and let the word <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> ſtand. And thirdly; ſo he doth: there it is, as it was; <hi>Root out that Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and Antichriſtian Sect of them.</hi> For the change (with which you would colour this paſſage) objected by <hi>Burton,</hi> ventilated in the <hi>Starre-Chamber,</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded afterwards by <hi>Heylin</hi> and <hi>Dow</hi> (all which you ſeeme to have read with double diligence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I mention them) was no more but this, from, <hi>that Sect,</hi> into, <hi>that Sect (of them:)</hi> I ſay the word <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> remaines (I have ſeene the very Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall:) So that your Crimination here is a notorious, and which is worſe, a wilfull Falſhood: And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your pretentions of holineſſe be, and great ſhew of zeale; we ſhall deſire the ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for his finall ſatisfaction, and to decide upon the whole matter betwixt us, but to remember this one Principle, that <hi>the divell is the father of lies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <p>27. But the Popes <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> being thus (as you falſly pretend) removed by my Lord of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123918:18"/> 
                  <hi>Canterbury,</hi> you ſay, <note place="margin">P 36.</note> 
                  <hi>the Pope, and his Cardinals, and their whole religion, begin to looke with a new face.</hi> Particularly it lies upon his <hi>Grace,</hi> that debating with the Ieſuite <hi>Fiſher,</hi> about the Popes Supremacy over the Church univerſall, he yeelds to S <hi>Peter</hi> a <hi>Primacie of Order:</hi> to the Pope, 1 a <hi>Primacie of Order;</hi> 2 <hi>A more powerfull Principality than other Churches;</hi> 3 <hi>An Apostolike Chaire;</hi> 4 <hi>A juriſdiction within his owne Patriarchate.</hi> Touching a Primacie of Order granted to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who ever denied it? <hi>Doe I deny it,</hi> ſayes <note n="t" place="margin">Ch. 5. div. 3.</note> D. <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his <hi>Conference</hi> with <hi>Hart? Then let me be ſmitten, not with the blunt weapon of the words of men,</hi> &amp;c. Touching thoſe priviledges granted the <hi>Pope;</hi> neither my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> nor any reformed Writer of note in this Church, doth deny them to him. And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly here had hee denied the firſt, it would have beene extorted from him by the third <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> of the ſecond Oecumenicall Councell: the ſecond, by the flat teſtimony of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> which the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> alledged: the third by S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> The fourth, by the ſixth <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, and <hi>Rufſinus</hi> his Teſtimony: and againe, every one of theſe, by other Teſtimonies <hi>ſans</hi> Number. But now, I pray, obſerve; Firſt, all theſe Priviledges are granted to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome; ſtante Imperio,</hi> and <hi>intra Romaniam:</hi> the Empire yet ſtanding, and within <hi>Romane</hi> ſoyle: ſo that the States and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the world being now changed, happily he may be brought to a new reckoning, as his <note n="*" place="margin">§ 25. Num. 13. What if the States and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the world be much chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Grace</hi> notes. Secondly, the moſt demonſtrative way to cut off his claime of <hi>Supremacy</hi> by divine Right, which is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123918:19"/> the point in queſtion, is to ſhew all his Greatneſſe to be founded upon poſitive Law, and in relation to the temporall State. So the Fathers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Calcedon, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that is the Regall City: And ſo <note n="x" place="margin">Can. 28. Ep. ad ſolit. vitam. agent.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rome is the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane City of all the Romane Soile.</hi> And the moſt demonſtrative way to cut off his claime of <hi>Univerſall Supremacy,</hi> is to <note n="y" place="margin">Prima pars huius Canonis ſatis perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuè docet Alexandrinum Epiſcopum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſe Poteſtatem in vicinis aliquot Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, ſic etram Romanum Epiſcopum ſua ſub poteſtate vicinas Italiae Regiones obtinuiſſe. Antiochenum Epiſcopum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as etiam vicinas Eccleſias gubernaſſe: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que horum quenquam in alterum ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritatem ſibi ſumpſiſſe: ergo tunc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris Romanus Pontifex nondum pro univerſali totius Eccleſiae Epiſcopo agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebatur. Oſiand. Ep. ad Con. Nic. Can. 6. Et Baron. ſcot. Apol. Tract. 5. c. 9.</note> limit him within the circuit of his owne Iuriſdiction. Thirdly, (as is ſaid before) it is neither ſtrange nor new in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to yeeld the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> all theſe Priviledges. I ſhall put this Authour in minde of King <hi>Iames</hi> onely, King <hi>Charles</hi> his bleſſed father: <note n="z" place="margin">Praemon. to all Chr. K.</note> 
                  <hi>Of Biſhops and Church Hierarchy, I very well allow (as I ſaid before) and likewiſe of Ranks and Degrees amongst Biſhops. Patriarchs (I know) were in the time of the Primitive Church, and I likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence that Inſtitution for orders ſake, and amongst them was a contention for the firſt place. And for my ſelfe (if that were yet the queſtion) I would with all my heart give my conſent that the Biſhop of Rome ſhould have the firſt ſeat, I being a Weſterne King would goe with the Patriarch of the Weſt. And for his Temporall Principality over the Signiory of Rome, I do not quarrell it neither; let him in God his name be</hi> Primus Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus inter omnes Epiſcopos, <hi>and</hi> Princeps Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, <hi>ſo as it be no otherwiſe then as</hi> Peter <hi>was</hi> Princeps
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123918:19"/> Apoſtolorum. How ſay you, Sir, whether is more bountifull to the <hi>Pope?</hi> King <hi>Iames,</hi> or the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury?</hi> he that can be content to admit him <hi>Patriarch of the Weſt;</hi> or hee that circumſcribes him within his <hi>Italique</hi> Dioceſſe? Had you beene to anſwer the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> here, you would have granted him none of all this. You would have told him plainly, the <hi>Pope</hi> was never of any credit in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, neither <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nor <hi>Primate,</hi> nor <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch,</hi> but a <hi>Monſter,</hi> and alwayes <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> or rather you would have told him, there was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Catholike Church</hi> at all. But it hath not beene our way in <hi>England</hi> to confute <hi>Ieſuites</hi> ſo: Wee are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that by the ſtrength of <hi>Truth,</hi> wee may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due <hi>Falſeſhood. Magna eſt veritas, &amp; praevalebit,</hi> but to drive out one untruth with another is an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and indeed, an unſucceſſefull way. Though our Adverſaries bee never ſo madde (ſaith <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ad Gal. c. 1.</note> St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>) yet it behoves not us out of the like love of contention to goe awry from the Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <p>28. But among all the Paradoxes charged here by you upon the Divines of our Church, this I ſtood amazed at. You ſay, They teach, <hi>That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Popes ancient Authority in</hi> England, <hi>and yeelding unto him all the Power that this day he hath in</hi> Spaine <hi>or</hi> France, <hi>would be many wayes advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and in nothing prejudiciall to the King.</hi> Good God! upon which of the <hi>Canterburians</hi> will this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox</hi> fall? Even upon his <hi>Grace himſelfe,</hi> you ſay; whoſe words ſtand upon the blacke liſt of your Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, thus. <hi>Cant. Relat.</hi> pag. 202. <hi>He that is not blinde, may ſee if hee will, of what little value the Popes power
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123918:20"/> in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Spaine <hi>is, this day, further then to ſerve the turnes of their Kings therewith, which they doe to their great advantage.</hi> Now that impudence it ſelfe ſhould not bluſh, out of theſe words to extort ſuch a prodigious concluſion. <note n="*" place="margin">Relat. of Relig.</note> Sir <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi> a man never ſuſpected ſure in the leaſt manner, to warpe towards <hi>Popery,</hi> diſcourſeth very largely, with what permutation of courteſies the <hi>Pope</hi> gratifies <hi>Popiſh Princes;</hi> and they, him: how hee ſerves them with his Diſpenſations and Excommunications, <hi>that hee may bee ſerved by them with their Executions:</hi> In all which, belike, hee doth but commend the like Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices to his owne King, and inſinuate <hi>that the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Popes power in</hi> England, <hi>would bee many wayes advantagious, and in nothing prejudiciall unto him.</hi> Hee that ſaies, men of haughty ſpirits, uſe <hi>proud</hi> and <hi>atheiſticall</hi> Diſcourſes, <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Their tongue goeth through the world, therefore fall the people unto them, and thereout ſuck they no ſmall advantage,</hi> doth by your reaſoning, herein exhort men to <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme.</hi> If theſe your candid Conſtructions may goe for ſolid Arguments, to prove <hi>Popery</hi> upon my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> nay if they induce not all reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, to believe him, as hee is, moſt cleare and innocent, and that more effectually, then any thing we can reply to you: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Farewell to all modeſty, truth, and piety. But let mee tell you touching theſe great Kings, <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> the experience of your Behaviour here, towards our and your Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, will rivet them faſter into the <hi>Popes</hi> Chaire, then all the Courteſies they can receive from the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:123918:20"/> 
                  <hi>Pope himſelfe,</hi> when they ſhall ſee that to reforme Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, will not be to vindicate their own juſt power in the government of the Church, nor to reduce their Kingdomes to the peaceable profeſſion of Chriſtian Truth; but to expoſe themſelves to new hazards, and indeed to breake one yoake to put on another, when they ſhall ſee that under pretence of Reformation, ſome men will ſtill bee heaving at the publike Government, and induce others to expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>eſpeé au poing;</hi> upon every occaſion, when they ſhall ſee the King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> that ſuſtaines ſo much unjuſt envie and inconvenience with the neighbouring world, for defence of the Goſpell, after the ſettlement of ſo many yeares, at as hard a paſſe to ſatisfie his Subjects in matters of Religion, as ever <hi>Themſelves</hi> were: When they ſhall obſerve all this to ariſe not from any accidentall matter of <hi>Fact;</hi> but from queſtions of <hi>right;</hi> from <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> infuſed into the people, by them that will be held the onely Architects of a Reformation: though (God knowes) they are farre from it: I ſay, when they ſhall obſerve and conſider all this; it may probably be thought, they will keep too cloſe, where now they are. And this is an immenſe ſcandall, and incurable would given by you to the Truth of God, which you may doe well to conſider of in your cooler thoughts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <p>29. Next it offends you, <note place="margin">P. 39.</note> my L. of <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſhould exempt himſelfe from the juriſdiction of the Pope, which he doth even by their owne Lawes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons. But I pray let not this be a point of Poperie: To any reaſonable man this one period is a ſufficient
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123918:21"/> confutation of your whole diſcourſe: unleſſe you can by ſome ſtrange art conclude this contradiction, That to ſhut out the Pope, is to let him in. <note place="margin">P. 41.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <p>30. But it offends you moſt of all: that he ſays, <hi>We and the Papiſts are of one religion:</hi> yet he gives you his reaſon withall: <note n="a" place="margin">Starre-Cham. Speech. p. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>There have been in the world of old, three Religions, Paganiſme, Iudaiſme, Chriſtianiſme: Two</hi> of theſe are falſe, ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Cont. Sabel. Gregales.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and if they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe each other, it is but as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> fought with the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> the <hi>third</hi> is the true. <hi>To theſe three,</hi> ſaith his Grace, <hi>later times have added a fourth, which is Turciſme.</hi> Now if theſe be all (and <hi>Brere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> who inquired thereabout with more diligence, than, I beleeve, ever you did, can <note n="c" place="margin">Inquir. c. 11.</note> tell us of no more) And we cannot reaſonably accompt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to be <hi>Iewes, Pagans,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> we muſt grant them <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and ſo we and they fall under the ſame gender of <hi>Religion.</hi> That <hi>in this Religion</hi> we <hi>differ,</hi> and that the <hi>Difference</hi> is certaine groſſe corruptions ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by them <hi>to the very endangering of ſalvation;</hi> this the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> defends, and you take notice of it: but this ſatisfies you not, it muſt be <hi>toto genere,</hi> a diverſe <hi>Religion.</hi> Now to bid us quit ſuch an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique diviſion, and not ſupply us with a new one; to put the Archbiſhops Reaſon in your mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and not gaineſay it with a better in your Text, is but the ſame prudence which you have uſed all your booke along. There is a great Schiſme in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetan</hi> Religion, and it begun <note n="d" place="margin">Paul. Iovi. L. 13.</note> much at the ſame time that <hi>Luther</hi> ſtirred in <hi>Germany,</hi> yet we count them all <hi>Mahumetans</hi> ſtill: and why may not diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be all <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> That ſome errours
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123918:21"/> and corruptions brought into a <hi>Religion,</hi> ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſifie it ſo, as to make it no more the <hi>ſame,</hi> is alike abſurd and unreaſonable, as if one ſhould ſay, an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound man</hi> is no more a <hi>man.</hi> We hold the <hi>ſubſtance of Religion</hi> in Common: the Papiſts with us, <note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme;</hi> which are S. <hi>Paul's Fundamentals.</hi> Our <hi>Faith,</hi> or Belief, is the ſame, as it is contained in, and explicated by the ſame <hi>Creeds:</hi> Our <hi>Baptiſme</hi> the ſame, which is the proper Badge, and <hi>Character</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Vide S. Aug. cont. Creſcon. l. 2. c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>of one Religion:</hi> when any of them returne from their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to us, we <note n="g" place="margin">Pource qui'l reſte encores quclque petite trace d'Egliſe en la Papauté &amp; meſme que la ſubſtance du Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſme y eſt demcurce joinct que Def<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficace du Bapteſme ne deſpend de ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lui qui Padmintstre, nous Confeſſons que cieux qui y ſont baptizez n'ont beſoin d'un ſecond Bapteſme. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Gallican</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>iterate not this.</hi> We thinke our ſelves bound to eſchew that arrogance and ſingularity, which <note n="h" place="margin">Iam illud quale eſt quod ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus Chriſtianis etiam Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricis dicitis, <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>te Chriſtiani<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. l. 3. Non eſt alius tam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius ſuperbiae tumor apud om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes qui ſe à Chriſti unitate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cindunt, quàm ſe ſolos eſſe Chriſtianos jactare, &amp; damnare caeteros. Auguſt. cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. lib. 4. Et in Epiſt. 169. ad Euſeb.</note> 
                  <hi>Optatus</hi> and S. <hi>Augustine</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended ſo ſharply in the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> Now if this be not to your mind, I pray tell us what <hi>ſpecificates</hi> a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; what latitude you will allow: Shall every difference <hi>in Religion</hi> be ſufficient to produce a <hi>new one?</hi> Then <hi>Geneva</hi> and you are not of one Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: For your new erection of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders</hi> to ſway in all Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Aſſemblies, and to voice in <hi>Matters of Faith, Geneva</hi> knowes not: Nay the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> as <note n="i" place="margin">D'Aubiga l. 2. c. 5.</note> an Hiſtorian of their owne Party tells us, offered to conforme themſelves to all the Ceremonies and Conſtitutions that had beene eſtabliſhed within the fifth Age of the Church; whereas you forſake them all. But if one <hi>difference</hi> ſerve not to diverſifie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123918:22"/> a <hi>Religion,</hi> may a few do it? Then are not you (a thing which we ſhall by no meanes acknowledge) of <hi>one and the ſame Religion</hi> with us. <note place="margin">P. 98.</note> For, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther differences betweene us, you ſay, your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men would never be induced to follow <hi>ſo much of the Maſſe as we retained here.</hi> If <hi>a few</hi> will not doe it, then <hi>how many,</hi> I pray? <hi>—depinge, ubi ſiſtam:</hi> how many Errours for Number, and how great for Quality, are of a juſt weight, to make <hi>Chriſtned men,</hi> no <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> When you goe about this Worke, you will finde your ſelfe brought, <hi>in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum lubricum &amp; periculoſum,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> cals it: ſo that you were better take the <hi>Stoicks</hi> counſell, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, to be quiet; and to ſtop this differencing of Religions, which is cutting a thread betwixt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and hell, at thoſe knowne bounds and limits, which common obſervation hath made: els, you will but venture into a <hi>ſoriticall</hi> Maze, out of which you will never be able to finde your way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <p>31. In like manner, it offends you, <note place="margin">P. 44.</note> that my Lord of <hi>Canterbury, in all that large Booke ſet out by him the laſt yeare, doth no where charge the Papiſts, with Schiſme, Hereſie, or Idolatry;</hi> nor any of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, you ſay, have done it, <hi>in earneſt, as farre as you can remember, in all your poore Lecture.</hi> Now truly I ſee little Cauſe, why you ſhould much confide in your owne poore Lecture: For doubtleſſe, moſt of theſe Collections were brought to your hand; and it is plaine, becauſe in the puzle of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting them, your faſhion is to put downe a Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and then another and another; and often by miſhap you light upon the ſame againe, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123918:22"/> downe you clap it againe, without any Care at all. Let the Reader but obſerve the manner, and he will be of my mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <p>32. But firſt, touching <hi>Schiſme:</hi> doth my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> no where charge the <hi>Papiſts</hi> with <hi>Schiſme?</hi> That he doth ſure very plainely: eſpecially in the 23. <hi>Sect.</hi> of his Book: where he ſhewes; in regard they thruſt us from them by Excommunications and Cenſures, and were obſtinate to continue in their owne Corruptions; the Schiſme was theirs. <hi>The Cauſe of the Schiſme is yours,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for you thruſt us from you, becauſe wee called for Truth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of Abuſes: A Schiſme must needs be theirs, whoſe the cauſe is.</hi> Againe, <hi>he makes the Separation, that gives the firſt just cauſe of it; not He that makes an actuall ſeparation upon a juſt cauſe preceding.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as he caſts upon them the <note n="k" place="margin">P. 145.</note> 
                  <hi>beginning of the Schiſme,</hi> ſo doth he <hi>the continuance of it.</hi> And if this be not to charge them with <hi>Schiſme,</hi> I know not what is: and inſiſting ſo largely, as he doth, upon this Argument, how could you miſſe it? You that a little before could ſee in his Booke, what was not there; <hi>the Popes Authority abſolutely vindicated, and commended to bee ſet up in England;</hi> Now cannot ſee what is there, <hi>The Papiſts charged with Schiſme:</hi> but no great marvell, this: <note n="l" place="margin">Tertul. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. cap. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Coecitatis enim duae ſpecies facilè concurrunt, ut qui non vident quae ſunt, videre videantur quae non ſunt.</hi> Or in S. <hi>Baſil's</hi> language: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>An eye indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and out of temper ſees not many things that are, and ſeemes to ſee many things which are not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:123918:23"/>
               <p>33. Next how ſhould we be ſure, neither the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop nor any of his Favourites charge the Papiſts with thoſe other two Crimes of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Idolatry?</hi> You that read them only to explore what is amiſſe, wil not report what you find, for you ſay, <hi>they abſolve them clearely in formall Termes of all thoſe three crimes,</hi> Schiſme, Hereſie, <hi>and</hi> Idolatry: <hi>Of</hi> Schiſme: <hi>becauſe they goe on in the practice of their Forbeares without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing any late Novations. Of</hi> Hereſie, <hi>becauſe their errors taketh no part of the Foundation away, but are only Exceſſes and Additions, conſiſting with all fundamentall Truth.</hi> Of Idolatrie: <hi>becauſe they teach not the giving of Latria to any Image or any Creature.</hi> Where that they <hi>clearly and in formall termes</hi> abſolve them of all theſe three, or any of the three, I am very confident will be found an untruth; for it is one thing <hi>to abſolve them by Deductions</hi> and Conſequences, of your making, and another to abſolve them <hi>clearly and in formall Termes,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt, which is <hi>Schiſme,</hi> as your report is falſe, ſo the reaſon given is weake and filly, for it is no Contradiction, but <hi>they may goe on in the practiſes of their forefathers,</hi> and yet be guiltie of <hi>Schiſme;</hi> by exterminating all thoſe, that will not ſubmit themſelves to the ſame vicious practices, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them; as it was ſhewed even now. The <hi>blame</hi> ever goes along with the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <p>34. For the ſecond, which is <hi>Haereſie:</hi> Even thoſe Errours of Rome which they hold not to be <hi>contra fundamentum,</hi> fundamentall errours: yet they hold them to be <hi>damnable;</hi> and if obſtinately perſiſted in, <hi>hereticall.</hi> Which is cleare by his <hi>Graces</hi> diſcourſe, <hi>Confer. p.</hi> 315. And elſwhere; as what ſay you to this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:123918:23"/> paſſage, <hi>p.</hi> 298. <hi>Therefore in this preſent caſe, there is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, great perill of damnable, both</hi> ſchiſme <hi>and</hi> Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, <hi>and other ſinne by living and dying in the Roman faith, tainted with ſo many ſuperſtitions, as at this day it is.</hi> Call you this cleare abſolving?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <p>35. Thirdly Concerning <hi>Idolatrie;</hi> though the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts be very nice in their doctrine here, yet it is well enough knowne, their <hi>Practice</hi> is groſſe: and how little my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> favours them either in their doctrine or practice, I leave the Reader to be his owne Iudge, if he pleaſe to peruſe the 33. <hi>Sec. Nu.</hi> 13. of his Conference, where upon occaſion of a propoſition taken out of <hi>Lammas,</hi> he putteth his adverſary to this queſtion. <hi>And now I pray</hi> A. C. <hi>doe you be judge, whether this propoſition doe not teach</hi> idolatrie: <hi>and whether the moderne church of</hi> Rome, <hi>be not growne too like to paganiſme in this point: For my owne part, I heartily wiſh it were not.</hi> And much more hath he there to this purpoſe; enough ſure to ſhew what credit may be given to this ſhameleſſe Calumniatour, who would make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Papiſts ſtand abſolved of theſe three Crimes, <hi>Schiſme, Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> clearly and in formall termes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <p>36. His like frequent overſtrainings in this kind, are an evident demonſtration, that he ſet himſelfe about this Worke, not out of any Love of Truth, but out of a wicked purpoſe to doe Miſchiefe, <hi>They teach,</hi> ſayes he, <note n="*" place="margin">P. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>that not only the People, but their moſt learned Clergie, Popes, Cardinals, Ieſuites, living and dying in their bitter oppoſitions and perſecutions of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, are in no hazard of Damnation, though they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:123918:24"/> never come to any particular Acknowledgement of their ſinfull opinions, and practices, following thereupon;</hi> as who ſhould ſay (for ſo the Words import) though <hi>knowing them</hi> to be ſinfull Opinions and practiſes, yet <hi>never acknowledging</hi> them ſuch, never repenting, nor asking God forgiveneſſe for them, they are ſtill in the way to heaven. Belike theſe <hi>Canterburians</hi> would be content to ſave the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals:</hi> though ſinning againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> for truth is, this were no leſſe. To make good this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, ſtand in his Margin this and ſuch like ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. <hi>The Corruptions of Rome materially and in the very kind and Nature, are leven, droſſe, hay and ſtubble, yet the Biſhop thought that ſuch as were miſled by Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or long cuſtom, or over-valuing the Soveraigntie of the Romane Church, and did in Simplicity of heart embrace them, might by their generall Repentance and faith in the merits of Christ, attended with Charity and other vertues, finde Mercy at God's hands.</hi> Reader, how ſay you, doth this come home to the <hi>Popes lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Clergie living and dying in bitter, and unrepented Oppoſitions, and perſecutions of Proteſtants?</hi> It was counted a Chriſtian Speech, that of <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. L. 6. c. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus</hi> to <hi>Novatus: Thou oughteſt to have endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any thing, rather then to rent the Church of God: To ſuffer for avoiding of Schiſme is a Martyrdome never a whit leſſe, nay indeed more Glorious, then for not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing to Idols.</hi> And S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> cites this from the mouth of an holy man, as he ſayes; <hi>That even Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome will not ſatisfie for Schiſme.</hi> Now then what Spirit, may we thinke, guides theſe men, that are ſo dearely affected to Diviſion and Combuſtion,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:123918:24"/> that rather, then faile to kindle a fire among us, doe harden their faces to ſlander, and in this bold Manner?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <p>37. Our <hi>Divines</hi> ſay; there is a Difference in Caſe of <hi>Schiſme</hi> or <hi>Hereſie,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Simple,</hi> and the <hi>Learned;</hi> the <hi>Miſled,</hi> and the <hi>miſleaders:</hi> They ſay; <hi>A man may be a good Proteſtant, and yet not damne all his forefathers:</hi> They ſay, <hi>we refuſe</hi> Communion <hi>with</hi> Rome <hi>in her Publike Service, being groſſe and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious; but in Charitie we hold</hi> Vnion <hi>with them and all the Church of Chriſt.</hi> Theſe and the like ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are ſcored downe here in his Margin as foule and impious: So that belike, the <hi>Contradictory</hi> of them would have better become the Pens of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. They muſt ſay, <hi>there is no difference betwixt Prieſt and people, ſimple and learned, Leaders and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, all are in a like Condition, all muſt to hell alike.</hi> They muſt ſay, <hi>no man can be a good Proteſtant that lives in charitie with a Papiſt;</hi> Nor <hi>can he be a good Protestant, unleſſe he damne all his Forefathers.</hi> What Cauſe there may be to repent of that pious and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Way, which hath hitherto beene inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by this our Church in defence of the Truth; and is moſt agreeable to Chriſtian moderation and the practice of the moſt holy times, I know not. But if this keene zeale were the only Weapon left, to deſtroy Poperie: And the Biſhops with their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents ſhould wipe their Pens, and give place to theſe fierie Champions; What Fields of honour would be wonne by their devouring ſword of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: what acceſſion made to the Proteſtant part; wiſe men know well enough, and time would teach
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:123918:25"/> the reſt, which is the beſt maſter to ſhew an errour, but the worſt to mend it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <p>38. Hitherto you have ſtood upon Generalls, you tell us; now you will come up cloſe to the <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> in particular points of <hi>Poperie:</hi> and for that purpoſe you propound us foure heads. <note n="*" place="margin">P 48.</note> 
                  <hi>Their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, their Hereſies, their Superstitions, their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Deſolation the Maſſe:</hi> In all which, ſay you, nay the <hi>groſſeſt</hi> of which; it ſhall appeare, that the <hi>Canterburians</hi> joyne with <hi>Rome.</hi> But having undertaken to preſent the Reader with ſuch paſſages as are objected to my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> from his owne pen, which was to be expected would raiſe a great Cloud over him: To ſee the ill luck of it; my worke is done even where it ſhould begin. For, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept about the Matter of <hi>Altars,</hi> in this next point of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I meet not with his Name cited above once or twice in all the reſidue of your Booke: ſo that you are faine to give him over at the firſt looſe: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word <hi>Canterburian</hi> runs through all, but to keep the worke alive, and your Reader in minde, at what marke ſpecially, be it right or wrong, he is to ſhoot. This muſt be ſwallowed, or els you have done juſt nothing, that all theſe men, whom you bring to the Barre for <hi>Canterburians,</hi> wrote by his ſpeciall encouragement, and direction; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome of them were his Elders and Anteceſſors in the Church, as D. <hi>Andrewes</hi> and D. <hi>White,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome of them were and are meere ſtrangers, and unknowne to him, ſo much as <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> which is moſt true, and will be avowed. Yea and when this is ſwallowed, yet you have done
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:123918:25"/> juſt nothing, for let the indifferent Reader, but uſe the helpe of your Margin to confute your Text, not diſtracting his owne eyes with paſsion or prejudice, and this quarrell is well nigh ended. Though were it otherwiſe, yet to affirme that the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> long before he was Archbiſhop, for theſe many yeares, hath held the Pens of all that have written in <hi>England</hi> amiſſe, and of none of them that have written right, is ſuch a wild Preſumption, as no man of any honeſty can ſay, and no man of Common Senſe will believe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <p>39. Concerning the <hi>holy Table</hi> or <hi>Altar,</hi> your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation is, <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſaith, <hi>that Worſhip, yea and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip or Adoration is to be given to the Altar.</hi> Let us ſee now, whether your Allegations in the Margin will come home to this; there we finde: <hi>Great reverence is due to the Body, and ſo to the Throne where this Body is uſually preſent;</hi> Marke you, <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> not <hi>Worſhip.</hi> But you ſay he gives, <hi>Venite Adoremus</hi> to the <hi>Altar,</hi> and no man can ſuppoſe that to be leſſe than <hi>Divine Adoration.</hi> Let us to your Margin againe: there we read thus: <hi>Therefore according to the Service-Book of the Church of England,</hi> (in this Compellation, <hi>Venite adoremus</hi>) <hi>the Prieſt and the People both are called upon for externall and bodily Worſhip</hi> of God <hi>in his Church.</hi> Marke you againe, <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> not <hi>of the Altar.</hi> Let the Reader peruſe the whole Paſſage, as it is ſet downe within the Bounds of a few ſhort Pages in his <hi>Starre-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Speech,</hi> and ſee if his conſtant expreſſion be not, <hi>Reverence to the Throne, Worſhip to God.</hi> 
                  <note n="q" place="margin">St. Sp. p. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid</hi> (ſayes his <hi>Grace</hi> there) <hi>we ſhould worſhip any thing, but God himſelfe.</hi> It is a rare confidence you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:123918:26"/> have in your Reader, that you dare ſet before his eyes your owne aſſertion and confutation of it both at once.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <p>40. Now that he ſaith, <hi>Great reverence is due to the Body, and ſo to the Throne where this Body is uſually preſent:</hi> Why ſhould it repent him of ſo ſaying? <note n="r" place="margin">Ad 2. Epiſt. Cor. Hom. 20</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith the ſame, and that even <hi>Terminis terminantibus:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Thou reverencest this Altar, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is placed the Body of Chriſt.</hi> And, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Why we ſhould challenge S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> of Idolatry; or why that ſhould be Idolatry in our <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> which was none in S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> cannot I imagine. But this you call, <hi>Sheltring ones ſelfe under the name of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; an</hi> 
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">P. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>uſuall thing,</hi> you ſay, <hi>with us here in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and we are faine to doe it, to keepe off our heads the indignation of the people.</hi> A ſpeech ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, that I thinke no Scholler, nor good Chriſtian but will diſdaine to read. Sir, excuſe our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in this, I pray: They have to doe with Adverſaries in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that are men of learning, and would make the world believe, they have carried all the ſuffrage of Antiquity from them, they cite the <hi>Fathers</hi> to diſcover their falſhood. And they have to doe with novelling <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> who, becauſe men, though of the beſt merit, are commonly undervalued in their owne times, muſt be encountred with names, and Authorities above exception. But chiefly they doe it, becauſe <hi>Errour</hi> being ſurreptitious and younger then <hi>Truth,</hi> we are bid by inſiſting upon the <hi>old
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:123918:26"/> Paths,</hi> to finde out the <hi>good Way,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> and to walke in that. And for this, did the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> 
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. de Spir. Sanct. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ ad Mat. Hom. 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. Lib. 3.</note> cite their <hi>Fore-fathers;</hi> ever by the Tracke of intermediate Times, aſcending to the Spring head of Truth. But you paſſe by all ancient Authours, and to make good your worke, betake your ſelves to other wayes, very farre different from ſcholaſticke arguments, thinking it ſufficient, you incurre <hi>not the indignation of the People,</hi> however abuſed and miſled by you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <p>41. But touching the point in hand; we are very much unſatisfied, ſince all Primitive Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Eaſterne and Weſterne, is ſo full for reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>holy places</hi> and <hi>holy things,</hi> whence it ſhould come, that to give them any regard now, ſhould be one of <hi>Rome's groſſeſt Idolatries.</hi> The <hi>Altar</hi> had ſo much honour, as by it ſelfe to denominate our whole Function, and Miniſterie ſometimes: as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari</hi> 
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Cypr. Ep. 4.9. &amp; paſſim.</note> 
                  <hi>deſervire; ab Altari avocare; ad Altaris Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterium, vel locum Sacerdotalem, indignum obrepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> to make a Schiſme in the Church, was <hi>erigere Altare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Altare.</hi> Catholike Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did honour it: <note n="y" place="margin">Quid enim eſt tam ſacrilegum, quàm Altaria Dei (in quibus &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando vos obtuliſtis) frangere, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, removere? in quibus vota populi &amp; membra Chriſti portata ſunt. Optat. lib. 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Conc. ſub A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gap. &amp; Men. Act. quint.</note> Hereticks and Schiſmaticks either break it, or as if it contracted ſome pollution, from former uſe, ſcrape it: Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Apoſtates, in contempt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:123918:27"/> of Chriſtian Religion, prophane it, <note n="z" place="margin">Theodoret. l. 4 c. 22. &amp; Nazianz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> dancing, or dicing, or otherwiſe abuſing it: One <note n="a" place="margin">Impudenter contra ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum Altare minxit. Hiſt. trip. l. 6. c. 32.</note> of <hi>Iulians</hi> Renegadoes did that to it by way of diſgrace, that I cannot civilly tell you; as if to diſhonour a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Altar,</hi> were to diſhonour <hi>Christ.</hi> And ſince all this is ſo, be you as petulant and as bold as you pleaſe, I ſhould rather deſire to be with them, that in contemplation of thoſe holy myſteries there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed to us approach thither, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> ſpeaks, with <hi>reverence and godly feare.</hi> In the meane time your falſhood is intolerable, that tell your Reader, my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> gives to the <hi>Altar,</hi> no leſſe then <hi>divine Adoration.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <p>42. This being paſt, you have little elſe to object to him, inſomuch that after the intervall of many pages, you are faine to <note n="c" place="margin">P. 85, 86.</note> rub up the ſame againe. In your next point, touching <hi>the Adoration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Elements,</hi> you are quite to ſeeke of any Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation at all: not one <hi>Canterburian</hi> can be brought to depone for it, except that you are angry at <hi>bowing,</hi> and call it our <hi>new adoration,</hi> that is our <hi>new Idolatry;</hi> our <hi>old Idolatry, kneeling at the Communion,</hi> you are content to paſſe over you ſay: but the new will not downe with you. How new or old it is in the Church of God; Much hath beene ſaid of late time: But whether you be a competent Iudge of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry the while, or whether our writings in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ought to be levelled by the <hi>Rubrick</hi> of your <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline, let any ſonne of this Church conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <p>43. Touching Images, Reliques, and Invocation of Saints; I finde of my Lord of <hi>Canterbury, Nè
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:123918:27"/> gry quidem.</hi> Was it, becauſe that in all his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings he toucheth no where upon thoſe Points? No. But where you cannot ſpeake ill of him, you will be ſure not to ſpeak well. How he writes of <hi>Images,</hi> I ſhewed before; Pray you read what he ſaith concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Invocation</hi> of Saints: <hi>Sect.</hi> 33. <hi>Num.</hi> 13. <hi>Though ſome of the ancient Fathers have ſome Rhetoricall Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes about it, for the ſtirring up of devotion (as they thought) yet the Church admitted not then of the invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them, but onely of the Commemoration of the Martyrs, as appeares clearely in S.</hi> Auguſtine. <hi>And when the Church prayed to God for any thing, ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be heard for the mercies and merits of Chriſt, not for the merits of any Saints whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If God muſt heare our prayers for the merits of the Saints, how much fall they ſhort of ſharers in the</hi> Mediation of Redemption? <hi>You may think of this. For ſuch Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as theſe, the Church of Rome makes at this day, and they ſtand (not without great ſcandall to Christ and Chriſtianity)</hi> uſed and authorized <hi>to be uſed in the Miſſall. For instance, upon the Feast of</hi> S. Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las <hi>you pray:</hi> That God, by the Merits and Prayers of <hi>S. Nicholas,</hi> would deliver you from the fire of Hell. And <hi>upon the Octaves</hi> of S. Peter <hi>and</hi> S. Paul, <hi>you deſire God</hi> that you may obtain the glory of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by their Merits. <hi>And on the Feaſt of</hi> S. Bonaventure <hi>you pray,</hi> that God would abſolve you from all your ſinnes by the interceding <hi>Merits of Bonaventure.</hi> How ſay you? if the <hi>Canterburians</hi> hold to this, I hope they are not gone from the Proteſtant Way: if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, why then are they <hi>Canterburians?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:123918:28"/>
               <p>44. In your next long Chapter there is but one drib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler againſt my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and that is in the matter of <note n="*" place="margin">P. 71.</note> 
                  <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> where preſſing againſt the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> that <hi>Baptiſme of Infants</hi> may be proved out of Scripture: (Mark you, <hi>out of Scripture;</hi> ſo he does not leave it to ſtand upon one leg of <hi>Tradition:</hi>) Thus he ſpeaks, <hi>Relat.</hi> p. 56. <hi>That Baptiſme is neceſſary to the Salvation of Infants in the ordinarie way of the Church (without binding God to the uſe and meanes of that Sacrament, to which he hath bound us) it is expreſſe in S.</hi> Iohn <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Except a man be borne againe of Water, he cannot enter. <hi>No Baptiſme, no entrance: nor can Infants creepe in any other ordinary way. And this is the received opinion of all the ancient Church. Infants are to be baptized, that their ſalvation may be certaine. For they which cannot helpe themſelves, muſt not bee left onely to extraordinarie helpes, of which wee have no aſſurance, and for which we have no warrant at all in Scripture.</hi> Hence your inference is: <hi>They avow</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that all thoſe who die in their infancie without Baptiſme, by whatſoever miſſe, by whoſoever's fault, are certainly damned, as farre as men can judge.</hi> A very liberall <hi>Concluſion,</hi> conſidering the narrow <hi>Premiſſes</hi> you had to deale upon: but you follow it; <hi>For Baptiſme is the ordinarie meane which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their ſalvation; which failing, ſalvation muſt be loſt; except we would dreame of extraordinarie Miracles, of the which we have no warrant.</hi> Now if a man analyze this huddle of words, and take the height of their ſenſe, it is, as if you had ſaid: <hi>They avow, that infants dying without Baptiſme, muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be damned, except they be ſaved.</hi> The Arch-Biſhops
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:123918:28"/> ſpeech falls into theſe Parts. 1 Baptiſme is the ordinary way of ſalvation appointed by Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 2 To ſave without Baptiſme, is a way extraordinary. 3 To truſt to extraordinary wayes, we have no warrant in Scripture. 4 Children are not to be expoſed to the perill of thoſe wayes, whereof we have no warrant. You will wring out of this; <hi>Children dying without Baptiſme, by whatſoever miſſe, by whoſoevers fault, are certainly damned:</hi> But before you can get off, a Whimſey takes you in the head, that you are faine to add; <hi>Except we will dream of extraordinary miracles, of which we have no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</hi> That is in ſence; <hi>Except God, who is not tied to meanes, pleaſe to ſave them by a way extraordinarie.</hi> So that <hi>à primo ad ultimum,</hi> your diſcovery is; <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dying without Baptiſme,</hi> according to the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburians, are certainly damned, except they be not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> Marry that to expreſſe, an honeſt and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe ſenſe, you will uſe ſuch an invidious phraſe, as <hi>dreaming of extraordinary miracles,</hi> it is but your wonted Candor. Call you it a <hi>miracle,</hi> for God to ſave by a <hi>way extraordinarie?</hi> that is, beſides the meanes and rules preſcribed to us? Or a beliefe of ſuch a ſaving, a <hi>dreame of miracles?</hi> The proper Matter and Subject of <hi>miracles</hi> is Nature, and things naturall: <note n="e" place="margin">Aquin. 1. q. 110. 4. c.</note> 
                  <hi>Miraculum dicitur, quod fit praeter ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem totius naturae creatae.</hi> But <hi>Salvation</hi> is a worke wholly <hi>ſupernaturall;</hi> and if you will tranſlate <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> thither, to workes ſupernaturall, then to ſave even by <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> is a <hi>miracle;</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ferrar. ad Aq. Cont. gen. l. 3. c. 101.</note> 
                  <hi>Et univerſaliter omne opus, quod à ſolo Deo fieri potest.</hi> And now ſee the addle language wee are fallen into; for thus it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:123918:29"/> will come to paſſe, that if to ſave <hi>by Baptiſme,</hi> be a <hi>miracle,</hi> and to ſave <hi>without Baptiſme,</hi> an <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e miracle,</hi> then ſome miracle is an <hi>ordinarie mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;</hi> which is abſurd, and a <hi>contradiction in terminis;</hi> every <hi>miracle</hi> being <hi>praeter ordinem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <p>45. The <hi>Canterburians</hi> (for ſo you will call them) do not love to be too buſie with damnation: you are thoſe men of wrath; in whoſe Power if it were to ſend poore ſoules to hell, 'tis to be doubted the whole world had beene conſumed by you ere this; as <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Ep. Ethic.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeakes of your like. The matter is; you ſtand not much upon <hi>Baptiſme</hi> or the <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> of it, you uſe to diſpute againſt it at home: but we here, hold it moſt neceſſary: and our <hi>Liturgie</hi> hath a ſpeciall <hi>Rubricke</hi> for <hi>Private Baptiſme</hi> in caſe of extremity, which I ſtill urge, to ſhew your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competency to judge of our Writings. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our or your doctrine be the ſounder in this point, I referre you to be inſtructed by your owne <note n="h" place="margin">P. 78, 79. &amp; ſeq.</note> 
                  <hi>Duplyes,</hi> who have ſet you to ſchoole in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and many other; I would we could ſee you rid your fingers handſomely of them. Take along wich you likewiſe K. <hi>Iames</hi> his opinion, and <hi>what evidence,</hi> ſay you, <hi>ought to be ſo demonſtrative as that?</hi> Who in the Conference of <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> reports, that to a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Miniſter, pierking againſt him with this Queſtion, <hi>Thinke you Baptiſme ſo neceſſary, that if it bee omitted, the child ſhould bee damned?</hi> Hee made this Anſwer: <hi>No: but if you, being called to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptize the child, though privately, ſhould refuſe to come, I think, you ſhould be damned.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
               <p>46. Behold another Innovation: <hi>They</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">P 73.</note> 
                  <hi>forbid Matrimony</hi> 
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
